Okay, so we've got two things going on
in the United States at the very same
time in this period. On the one hand,
we've got big strides toward national
economic unification, but on the other,
that unification is encouraging more
regional distinction across the United
States. And if that sounds confusing,
don't worry, cuz I'm about to explain it
real nice for you. So, if you're ready
to get them brain cows milt, let's get
to it. Okay, so as we've seen in this
unit and in the last unit, there's a
persistent tugof war in the early
republic between whether it's the United
States or the United States. In other
words, in the late 18th and early 19th
century, one of the main arguments among
Americans was whether national concerns
or regional concerns were more
important. And in this period, we see
both developing at the exact same time.
And so, let's start by considering the
efforts of legislators to strengthen the
national economy. Oh, and by the way, if
you want note guys to follow along with
this video and all my videos, check the
link in the description. Okay, first of
all, remember from the last video that
thanks to Napoleon kind of giving up on
France's presence in the Americas, he
went ahead and sold the US to Louisiana
territory uh real cheap. And that did a
lot of things, but one of the most
important things it did was to open the
Mississippi River to US merchant ships
so that they could get their trade on up
and down the western frontier. And this
got even better when steam ships were
introduced because now the trade vessels
could travel up river as well as down
river. Anyway, that development really
benefited Americans in the south and the
west, but it ended up hurting Americans
in the northeast because land routes
between it and the Ohio River Valley
were less attractive to merchants owing
to the difficulty of overland travel
compared to water travel. Although to be
fair, with the opening of the Eerie
Canal in 1825, which connected the
Northeast with the more western farms,
that difficulty would certainly lessen.
But regardless, in response to the
northeastern economic melancholy,
Congress approved the construction of
the Cumberland Road in 1811, which would
facilitate overland trade between
Maryland and Ohio. And look, I'm not
just flapping my mouth hole about
federally funded infrastructure for
funsies. No, I saved that for my daily
podcast, infrastructure infrastructure.
I said more canals. The reason why this
is important is because all of these
developments work to link the various
regions of the United States into an
interdependent economic hole. For
example, southern planters could more
easily transport their raw materials,
most notably cotton, to the factories in
the north, and northern manufacturers
could more easily transport their
finished goods to sell in the south, in
the west, and so on and so on. So, all
that to say, in this period, we see the
construction of metric buttloads of
roads and canals, all of which just kept
knitting the various regional economies
tighter together. But for sure, the
granddaddy of all legislative programs
to boost the national economy was the
introduction of a series of policies
known as the American system proposed in
1824 by the speaker of the house from
Kentucky, our boy Henry Clay. Now, just
like I mentioned earlier, the American
system was just another effort to grow
the national economy and simultaneously
knit together the regional economies
into a tighter interdependent hole. Now,
it was definitely a complex set of
policies, but you really need to
remember three of its main emphases.
First, the American system proposed a
dizzying array of federally funded
infrastructure projects paid for by
tariffs and land sales which would
include roads and canals that would
benefit farmers and merchants in the
south and west. And then second, Clay
proposed protective tariffs to stimulate
domestic industry. Now, what in the
fresh heck is a protective tariff? Well,
a tariff is a tax on goods imported from
other countries. And the protective part
of it means that the tax is high enough
on those foreign goods that people are
more likely to buy goods made in
America. So, the tariff protects
American manufacturers and gives them an
economic boost. What's that? You want a
concrete example? You know I got you,
boo. Behold the tariff of 1816, which if
you're paying attention, does come
before the formal introduction of the
American system in 1824, but it's still
part of the overall package. Anyway, the
tariff of 1816 was passed in response to
British merchants flooding the American
market with cheap manufactured goods.
You see, they had a large stockpile of
goods that have been building up as the
result of Jefferson's embargo act and
the War of 1812. And so, they sold these
goods to Americans at a fraction of what
they were worth. And American
manufacturers could no longer compete on
prices. So, Congress passed the tariff
which raised prices on those British
goods and made Americans more likely to
buy Americanmade goods. But the thing to
remember about this tax is that it was
the first tariff enacted whose main goal
was not to raise revenue for the federal
government, but instead to protect and
bolster domestic industry. And so,
because this tariff was framed not in
terms of the federal government seeking
profit, but rather as a matter of
national security against Great Britain,
it was pretty popular across the various
regions of the country. However, in the
next couple of videos, I'll tell you how
that support started to wne as the
economic situation of the country began
changing. But alas, I get ahead of
myself. Anyway, the third part of Clay's
American system was the establishment of
the second bank of the United States.
Now, Hamilton's first bank of the United
States was created under a charter of 20
years. And in 1811, Congress did not
renew that charter. So, the bank went
the way of Alexander Hamilton himself,
which is to say it suffered an early
death. So, Clay proposed the creation of
a second national bank to regulate
public credit issued through local banks
throughout the nation. Additionally, the
bank issued a national currency. And all
this worked to bind the various regions
of the country together into a tighter
national hole. And at the same time, it
promoted regional specialization. In
other words, it encouraged each region
to do what they were best at doing. The
north should focus on manufacturing. The
south should focus on the cultivation of
cotton. And the west should focus on
food production. Okay. So, up to this
point, you might have the impression
that regional differences were starting
to disappear as a result of this big
national hugfest. But here's where I
tell you, not so much. No, this
unification of the national economy
actually worked to bring out the
differences between the various regions.
You see, since the infrastructure to
connect the various regions was
multiplying rapidly, each region could
specialize in what they did best and
rely on importing goods from other
regions to make up for what they lack.
For example, in general, southern states
specialized in agriculture. And in this
period, cotton became the dominant crop
grown and exported from the south. And
then northern states majored in
manufacturing and depended on importing
raw materials from the south in order to
produce those manufactured goods. But
with the overultivation of the southern
soil, many planters took their enslaved
laborers with them and moved west. And
with the session of Florida to the
United States via the Adams Onus treaty,
they moved further south as well. And
then many of those planters who did not
migrate west shifted to the sale of
enslaved people to the western planters
since by 1808 the international slave
trade was banned. So the point is the
fact that regional economies were
becoming more distinct also made them
more unified since they needed each
other in order to prosper. But despite
all of that, the growing regional
distinction meant that regional
attitudes about economic policy and
slavery contrasted sharply. And let me
give you an example of each first. In
terms of economic policy, let's talk
about the panic of 1890. Now, a panic is
an old word for an economic depression.
And this particular panic was caused
directly by a slew of irresponsible
practices carried out by the national
bank. You see, its regional branches in
the west had been reckless about loaning
money to Western farmers on the
assumption that economic growth would
continue and the farmers would be able
to pay back what they owed. Now, this is
what we call speculation, and it's a
very risky gamble, especially for a
national stinking bank. In essence,
these farmers borrowed more money than
they had collateral to back it up if
things went bad for them. Anyway, in
1818, the National Bank wanted to
tighten up the money supply in the
United States and reduce the amount of
credit available to its regional
branches. And for all sorts of
complicated reasons that you don't
really need to know, that act led to a
rapid financial collapse as banks called
in their loans and farmers were not able
to pay them. The result was mass
foreclosures on farms, which then led to
financial hardship in the manufacturing
north since they were no longer able to
receive the raw materials they needed.
And so when Congress started debating
about how to best solve this problem,
regional differences flared up quick,
fast, and in a hurry. Northern
manufacturers wanted more tariffs to
protect their industries from
international competition. But southern
planters argued that the tariffs would
raise prices on goods that they needed
to survive at the very time when
European demand for their agricultural
goods were decreasing. And then many
common farmers felt that their needs
were being ignored as elites argued
about how to best protect their own
interest. And so for many Americans,
this panic led to a significant mistrust
of the expansion of federal power,
especially represented by a federal
bank. And then second, regional
differences also flared up with respect
to the question of slavery. Now, as you
probably know by now, slavery was the
dominant labor system in the south and
to a growing degree in the west. But the
dominant labor system in the north was
wage labor, also known as free labor, to
contrast it with enslaved labor. And I
don't really have time to explain the
intricacies of why each one saw the
other as a threat, but just know that
they did, and that we'll come back to
that in a future video. Anyway, this
antagonism between enslaved labor and
paid labor was held in a delicate
balance owing to the equal distribution
of these state senators in Congress. In
1820, there were 44 senators in
Congress, and they were equally split
between slave state and free state
interests. And they found a way to live
together with that kind of balance, even
if it was uncomfortable sometimes. But
then something happened that freaked
everybody's crap out. The Missouri
territory applied for statehood, and as
a territory, slavery was permitted. So,
the assumption was that Missouri would
join the Union as a slave state. But
that of course would tip the Senate
balance in favor of slave states. Not to
mention that because of the three-fifths
compromise we talked about in unit 3, a
new slave state would also boost their
numbers in the House as well. And so the
northern states were, to put it mildly,
not happy about that. But don't worry,
things are about to get worse. Yeah. The
tension was increased by the
introduction of the Talmage Amendment
proposed by New York Congressman James
Talmage. And it stated that Missouri
could enter the Union only on the
condition that it banned slavery and
then gradually emancipated the enslaved
people that already lived there. So,
southern congressman flat out rejected
the amendment and so northern
congressmen retaliated by refusing to
admit Missouri as a state. And you have
to understand the stakes here because
southerners felt that this move was an
existential threat to their own
political power. You see, since the
northern population had grown at a much
faster pace than the southern
population, northern states would always
hold a majority in the House of
Representatives since seats in that
house are gained by population. And so,
the balance between the North and the
South in the Senate was the only hope
they had at protecting their interest in
maintaining and expanding slavery. But
if Missouri came in as a free state,
then the Senate too would tip in favor
of northern interest. And to
southerners, that was a big heck no. But
don't worry, because here comes Henry
Clay writing on that noble steed called
compromise to save the day. Yes, it was
Henry Clay who introduced the Missouri
Compromise, otherwise known as the
Compromise of 1820. And there are two
important effects of this legislation
that you need to remember. First, the
compromise would admit Missouri as a
slave state, but also admit Maine as a
free state, thus upholding the balance
in the Senate. Second, the path for the
future expansion of slavery was
codified. It was agreed that from here
on the 3630 line of latitude, which was
Missouri's southern border, would create
the geographical division of slavery in
the United States. Slavery could exist
below that line, but not above it. And
as it turned out, this compromise was
enough to make everyone kind of happy,
but it wouldn't be long before those
same debates flared up again as more
Americans migrated into the Louisiana
territory. But next time, it would be
worse. But I get ahead of myself. We'll
have to save that juicy tail for another
video. Well, okay. You can click here to
watch my other videos from unit 4, or
you can click here to grab my video note
guides, which are going to help you get
all the contents of this course firmly
crammed into your brain folds. And hey,
I'm glad you came around and I'll catch
you on the flip-flop. Himler out.